welcome everyone to the first lecture of new course deep learning for natural
processing time for quantum i'm lecturer here in the computer science
although I spend most of my at a company called deepmind in
London four days a week there and this will be a collaboration between
computer science department and deep mind and so we we've got for you a range
different speakers mostly from deepmind a few other places and you get
meet during the course of this lecture so let's get started so that the
of first starting side is why you be here and take this course
the key reason you should take this we're interested in language this
is going to be about language is gonna about the computational processing of
and how it relates to intelligence artificial
is a pretty hot topic at moment in in computer science and
in general and hopefully by the of this you'll agree with me that
is really one of the most aspect of intelligence worthy
of a study so historically language linguistics has been very
associated with AI maybe some say too much so so through the
half of the 20th century a lot of and I was language-based not not a
lot of progress was made people away from language recently quite
lot of progress has been made and now coming back to this problem of
do we deal with intelligence and language is cool because it's
it's how we communicate but it's than just communication so we
just simplistically think of is a way of conveying ideas
us but we can think of a way of provoking concepts in people we speak to
if i say the word dog that's just a wave but now all of you I can vote
concept of a doll little for like a very creature in your
mind and you all have slightly different concepts of dog but just by using the
the medium of language I can invoke that in you so language more than
it's a it's an interesting phenomena
when we still don't really that well so that's why this
on how to process language as well seeing this course but also we
fully understand how humans learn how children come to be so
language so quickly with so that stimulus
ok so hopefully that's a bit of high-level motivation so some
nitty-gritty details about this course is a webpage anything is anything
interesting on it yet maybe they will be later on we'll see these
are being recorded on how difficult it proves to
hopefully I've got to put them up so you can review them but it may take
time then then i might have to do there's no textbook for this course
and partly because a lot of the things we'll discuss a client new and most of
things especially the second half for the course relates to research
done in the last two or three but there are some good general
text is a very new textbook on deep from me a good fellow and and
men do it all for deep learning you get that in physical form or the
has the PDF that you can so that's a very useful
it covers deep learning in does and this chapters that are
relevant particular recurrent network chapter which could be
useful to you and then there's a lot of textbooks in general machine
learning so particularly the the Murphy machine-learning out lift off
earth also there but that's Murphy the bishop takes textbook you'll
those in the library's i think i've in the past for machine learning
so they may be in your in your libraries obviously the lectures
runs on tuesday at 46 and the other on Thursday also from 46 slightly different
other courses in in cs5 allocated two hours for the
that doesn't mean elections going to go for two hours but i just thought
I'd allocate plenty of time I find one hour bit too short sometimes we're going
to have lots of invited speakers some of week so i might have we might put
of two hour long lectures back-to-back in one of the slots on
weeks that might be quite sure i'll try that you know beforehand
what's what's happening in this week we'll probably use most of
two hours today and and on thursday so there will be no lectures next week
so most of the people involved in the are away in Germany on a seminar
next week so there's gonna be no they will however be practical
week so don't forget that so they're gonna be seven practical
I think they're on mondays and fridays but you should check the
timetable you've got some excellent in brandon yiannis an
issue all graduate students here in the department and experience deep learning
so they should be very handy for you learning the practical
of the course they should be of those from six to eight and
finally the assistant will be a total take-home exam of the form that
will MC students amongst you familiar with from last term
ok so practical details rough lecture so I I make no promises that i
keep this all that these will be people giving lectures but roughly
we're going to do is today after my introduction
I'll introduce wangling from a deep mind who's going to give you an introduction
or or hopefully a review of basic learning and neural network
from first principles how to up to the backpropagation
and then on Thursday and Griffin step we'll talk about lexical
and i also have I think chris is going to come up as well maybe talk a
bit about what we hope to do in practical sessions and I said week
too no lectures so that your next week week
i'm going to talk about recurrent networks and language modeling
very issues involved in those I'm how to make them go fast then after
we're going to run through lots of applications of these models like go
them all here but i will have a of guest lectures from deepmind
hopefully i'm jeremy from video will up and tell you a bit about gpus
why GPUs are important for these sorts models and you the graphic graphics
unit if you haven't come it before they happen to be the
device of choice to run models on so hopefully we'll get a
letter from video on those and then that you have a second after this course will
look at applications of these in translation and speech and
understanding so I prerequisites so this is not meant to be
introduction to machine learning so hopefully you've all got some
of machine learning you may find this a bit opaque
so at least you should understand of taking courses in linear algebra
probability so the courses that student here in their
year computer science degree are adequate and that is what's
those courses adequate maybe not you remember from them so if you
can't remember that review those ideas not going to do anything
challenging in those areas basic ideas from those areas will be
so machine learning other side is introduction machine learning course
will be very useful if you've taken introduction of machine learning
that was offered last term or year here in the department or
equivalent at the very least should have an idea of how to what
means to train and evaluate machine model and how to split up your
data and how to keep your test separate from your training data
all these basic issues machine learning so you can actually work out
your model works or not you should what overfitting generalization and
regularization mean that's very
learning is all about that's the whole point
how to generalize from what we see in past to what's going to happen in
future optimization so you should have knowledge of what
gradient descent is stochastic gradient hopefully its various variants
a great and such things hopefully come across these if not some reviewing
be in order and also basic algorithm flight linear regression
and definitely a little of neural networks and back
propagation when will go through those but hopefully that will be a
for you rather than introduction finally for the practicals so
impractical to be implementing these are you going to need to know how
program we're not going to teach you program we're not going to tell you
language or talking to use those so it's up to you what you
to do I've listed some here that a popular so
torch tensorflow piano and and dinette these are all good tool kits for
your network models torches lowers a programming language the others
python-based or C++ so you should choose you're comfortable with and
make use of that and there you're going to be given a lot of help in
to program while learning those tickets so you should be confident in
going out to pick up those things ok so going back to that the court in
this course is about from the you can guess deep learning for
language processing there's a lot more than natural language
and computational linguistics and deep learning so that this is not a
course in comfort linguistics you shouldn't
out the end of this course thinking deep learning is the answer to all
in language or that we're going get to a i simply by building bigger
bigger recurrent neural networks course is really about looking at
developments in deep learning and and some particular successes
these models are very effective lots of things or areas within
effective so it's just a caveat to with two not not feel that this is
there is to know about machine language and also language in
in particular in terms of where we're at iron language we still very much
the surface of a the phenomenon is language we're a long
from real conceptual reasoning about and so whether the techniques
will discover in this clip that discussing this course will get us there
an open question but you should have open mind about these areas and and
feel that while these techniques impressive results they're not the
way of approaching things so we a brief review of some of the
that we might look at this course hopefully to stimulate some interest so
understanding is a core problem we want we want to solve in in
processing so we want models that can hear or read texts and
what is being said one way of understanding is to ask
so a classic problem in understanding is with your
comprehension so later on in the will discuss reading
models this particular is from a data set we created
the deep mind where we took news this one from the CNN about
Jeremy Clarkson punching his executive and then ask questions of them
train models to try to answer these if you look at this particular
question is asking who will not press against Jeremy Clarkson if you
at the article to answer this the model needs to be on a
stitch together a few bits of different of information needs to understand
the opening sentence that it was a who will not press charges and
later on in the article producers named as poison time and so a
needs to be able to put those together and understand that
a first event of of the assault and in the second event of the naming of
producer and be able to put these bits of information together so it's a
cool and challenging task and it's one we're a long way from doing
but we have some models you do respective respectively on such
tasks will look at those and one of the areas weird deep learning has had a lot
success in language is an article
asks so any task we are trying to take a usually a sequence and convert
it into it structure normally another
so classic example to the recognition in speech recognition
get a sequence of audio signals and want to transduce that into the
text that was spoken machine is also another classic
task when you get a of symbols in one language in
case French and you want to that into the equivalent
sequence in English if you put these you can do things like
translation and if you to apps like google translate on the
now you can speak to them they will and convert that audio signal
intertext i'll try and translate that into another language for you and
speak that back to you up until a few years ago these all
problems were done with certain in the last couple of years all
these properties industrial systems moved to deep learning models
big recurrent neural networks a recognition machine translation
all done with big recurrent networks and text-to-speech as well is moving
that direction so we'll cover these the course of a couple of weeks
fun sort of tasks that will look later on to become popular is image
so one of the great things deep learning an approach to
language is a is it the same that we use for processing
now so doing has had a lot of in image recognition object
and classification and we're now using the same models
processing images as we're using the language it becomes very easy to put
together so now it's straightforward to take a model that
objects and images and stick together with a language model that
language train these together we can train models to caption
if we have examples of images and their captions and we can also train
to answer questions about images so this is a data set that was produced
task visual question answering have lots of images and questions
those images what's happening so straightforward questions in a
class by my get right like what is the holding two more influential
like does this man have twenty-twenty vision obviously their
model needs to understand something vision being related to the
wearing that being an indication he probably doesn't have
twenty-twenty vision so I'm this one of the real contributions of the move
to deep learning language processing has the ability to the bolt together
from vision and other modalities simply and get these sort of models
so we're not going to deal too much with structure
they're the sorts of things that that learning does well in language at
moment is still very much at the behaviorism end of the spectrum that is
input to output so we're a long from any sort of conceptual
about things and in this will mostly stay low level and
and look at sort of how do we transduce an audio signal into the the text that
along with that or a French into english sentence but you
should never forget there's a lot more than just these shallow aspects
so here are some classic examples of us at a random selection of language
that we should not forget when when trying to process language so the
one there is a classic since so I saw a duck is it a is a
ducking is in the physical motion or the the bird got idioms so one of
wonderful things about language is its compositionality so language follows
looks like sort of logical rules how we can compose the words to
get the meaning of a sentence so he the goal the composition is
the same as he takes the ball we're just changing that the noun
there but it doesn't always work in the classic medium of he kicked
bucket of course that doesn't mean about kicking or buckets that
he died so languages compositional when it's not and this is one of
most challenging things for any models it's easy to write
logical systems and processes simple but as soon as you let that
in the wild someone will say that doesn't fit your logical
and you'll have to deal with this of thing so at the end of the
will touch a bit on these issues how we start to think about the the
of hierarchical structure we see in the final example there is
called a winograd schema which these reference problems where if you
that sentence with the two endings so the board not fit
the box because it was too big four it was too small if you switch
and small it switches what they it to so it was too big then the
ball hits the ball which was too big it too small that's the box which was
small so getting your competition computational mole to be able to tell
difference between those two is very but it has to have a notion of
physical world of boxes and balls size and how they could fit within
other so that's one of the really challenges in language processing
we're a long way from solving but talk a bit about these sort of
problems later on in the
ok so that's why I sort of introduction and motivational opening so the rest
this lecture I'm going to hand over wangling is going to give you a
review of how to count and add and maybe a bit about neural
as well with the aid of some sesame street characters