Okay, good morning everyone.
We're gonna get started with our
first tutorial in this room.
This morning, we have variational
inference, foundations and
modern methods.
So we have three really
amazing speakers this morning.
First, we have Dave Bly,
who's a professor of statistics and
computer science at
Columbia University.
We also have Rajesh Ringanak,
who is a PhD student at
Princeton University.
And Shakir Mohamed,
who is a senior research
scientist at Google Deepmind.
And, I don't wanna eat into
their time anymore, so
without further ado,
let's get started.
>> Thanks, Tamara.
Thanks for the opportunity to tell
you about variational inference.
Rajesh and Shakir and
I have prepared this tutorial,
Variational Inference,
Foundations and Modern Methods.
We prepared about a seven and
a half hour tutorial, so
I'm gonna get started.
Also I wanna mention that two of us
are jet lagged, and Shakir is not
a morning person, so but I imagine
many of you are in the same boat.
Also, the echo is distracting but
I'll get used to it.
So we'll start with
just some pictures.
These are pictures of things you
can do with variational inference.
This is a picture of overlapping
communities discovered from
a huge network.
This is a picture of topics.
We'll talk about topics in
more detail in a little bit,
found from two million articles on
the New York Times using a laptop.
This is a picture of using
variational inference to learn about
scenes, and to do control and
reinforcement learning.
This is a picture of a genetics
analysis at large scale,
a important model in population
genetics the [INAUDIBLE] model
fit with variational
inference at large scale.
This is a picture of a neuroscience
analysis of a large FMRI data set.
And finally, here are some pictures
representing how we might do
compression, or generate content
using variational inference.
I know I didn't say anything about
any of those pictures, but I wanna
give you the sense of the breadth of
applications of variation inference.
And there's one more,
this is the picture of analyzing 1.7
million taxi trajectories using
a probabilistic programming system
called Stan,
using variational inference.
Okay, so all those pictures and
the extra picture
go through what we like to call
the probabilistic pipeline.
In a cartoon, this is the
probabilistic pipeline where, okay,
can you see that little green dot?
And you can't see it over there.
Where we take our knowledge and
our question that we wanna ask about
some data, use it to make some
assumptions about the data,
and turn those assumptions
into a model, okay?
The model has hidden quantities,
which are represented as hidden
random variables and
observed quantities.
Then we square our data and
our model together,
to discover patterns in the data.
And we use those discovered
patterns to form predictions, and
explore the data, answer the
question that we started out with.
I like this picture because
customized data analysis has
become important to many fields.
And this pipeline separates these
key activities, making assumptions,
doing computation, and then applying
the results of those computations.
And this makes it easy to
collaborate with domain experts on
problems, and statistics,
and machine learning.
Now you can see from this picture,
that the key algorithmic problem is
how to take your model that has
hidden and observed variables, and
your data, and uncover the values
of the hidden variables given
the observed variables.
That's inference, that's the subject
of this morning's tutorial.
Inference answers the question, what
does my model that I developed based
on my knowledge and
my questions say about the data?
And our goal in building
probabilistic machine learning as
a field is to develop general and
scale-able approaches to inference.
We wanna be able to lubricate this
pipeline so that we can try many,
many different models, answer many
different kinds of questions,
analyze many different
kinds of data.
But to do that we need easy ways
to compute about each model with
our data sets.
And we need to compute
with them at scale.
Moreover, this picture is
actually hiding a loop, right?
Really what we wanna do once
we've lubricated this pipe line,
is go back and revise our model,
and work with data and models.
In this loop where we criticize
our model, revise our model,
do inference, look at the results,
criticize, revise, and so on, okay?
This is our vision for
probabilistic machine learning.
Okay, so first I wanna
give some main ideas and
historical context for
variational inference.
The problem of general and
scale-able inference
with probability models.
So the basics, I'm sure many
of you are familiar with this.
A probability model is a joint
distribution of hidden variables z,
and observed variables x, okay?
So p of z comma x.
Inference about
the unknown variables,
about the hidden variables, happens
through the posterior, all right?
That's the conditional distribution
of the hidden variables given
the observations, p of z given x,
and that's the posterior.
And as you all know,
that is the ratio of the joint
and the marginal probability
of the observations p of x.
For most interesting probabilistic
models that we study in machine
learning, that denominator,
p of x is intractable,
we can't compute it exactly.
And so,
we can't compute the posterior, and
that's why we appeal to
approximate posterior inference.
That's why we used things like
MCMC and variational inference.
You'll see this picture
several times this morning.
So variational inference
in a nutshell,
turns inference into
an optimization problem.
So remember our goal is to
compute p of z given x.
And the way variational inference
works is, sorry I'm gonna point at
this screen, is first we positive
variational family, what's called
variational family, of distributions
over the latent variables.
Okay, so
this is denoted q of z semicolon nu.
All right, so nu are what
are called variational parameters.
They index this family
of distributions over z,
over the hidden variables.
And I've represented that
in this picture here,
where it's a set, right?
This circle here is a set of
distributions over z, indexed by nu.
Each point in that circle is a
different setting of the variational
parameters.
The goal of variational inference,
is to fit the variational parameters
nu to be close in KL divergence
to the exact posterior.
Just for kicks,
I'll walk over here now.
So, what we wanna do is we wanna
start at some value of nu, nu init.
And we wanna search through
this family of distributions,
using an optimization procedure, to
get to new star, where new star is
close in some sense to the posterior
distribution that we care about,
p of z given x.
And we are, in this tutorial, we're
going to be close in KL divergence.
We are gonna, we want a nu
whose value is close in terms
of KL of q of z and p of z, okay?
And that's the objective function.
All right, so in this way,
we've turned inference into
an optimization problem.
Well, MCMC forms
a Markov chain whose
stationary distribution is p of z
given x, in variational inference,
what we do is we posit this
family of distributions.
Then we search through
that family to find
the member that is closest in KL
divergence to the exact posterior to
the thing we care about, all right.
Now here we're gonna talk
about KL divergences.
There are other divergence measures.
You could look at KL pq.
You can look at other things.
And those correspond to other
methods, like EP, and BP, and
other things which are also could
be more broadly construed as
variational inference.
But just this morning,
at least we're gonna focus on KLqp,
all right?
It's an interesting line of research
to look at other divergences,
but we won't do that here.
Okay, here's a picture, here we're
taking a mixture of gaussians.
So these are data from a mixture of
gaussians, and as we run variational
inference, we are finding better,
and better approximations of,
in this case, the posterior
predictive distribution.
And so you can see that we
converge on a posterior predictive
distribution that
looks pretty good for
a mixture of gaussians
of these data.
And then we'll get to what these
quantities are later on, but
this is something like
the KL divergence.
This is the KL divergence
up to an additive constant.
And you can see that
we're getting closer and
closer to exact posterior.
Okay, so this is, in a nutshell,
stare at this picture.
This is variational inference.
Okay, we thought we would.
I don't know where to stand.
I have to admit.
We thought we would say a little bit
about the history of these methods
because they've become
important lately.
What variational inference really
is, is it's adapting ideas from
statistical physics,
to probabilistic inference.
And it's hard to know when ideas
start, but arguably, this idea began
in the late 80s with the work of
Peterson and Anderson from 1987.
Who I think were physicists, and
used mean field methods
to fit a neural network.
And this idea was picked up by
Mike Jordan's lab at MIT in
the early 1990s.
These were people like Tommy
Jaakkola, and Lawrence Saul, and
Zoubin Ghahramani, some of
the pioneers of this method who
generalized variational inference
to many probabilistic models.
So there's a nice paper by
those four authors from 1999
that reviews that work.
In parallel, Hinton and
Van Camp also developed mean field
inference for neural networks,
and possibly not aware of
the Peterson and Anderson work.
And they connected that
idea to things like
The Algorithm that we all know.
Which led to variational methods for
other kinds of models,
like mixtures of experts, and HMMs.
One of the other pioneers here
was the late David MacKay.
Actually, there's a whole chunk
of years missing in this history.
So in the late 90s and early 2000s,
a lot of machine learning
researchers developed
variational inference for
specific models and
generalized in some sense.
We'll get to some of those
generalizations in a little bit.
And now today, there's a flurry of
new work on variational inference
and that work is about making
variational inference scalable,
easier to derive, faster.
To give it better fidelity and to
apply it to more complicated models,
and applications.
And modern variational inference,
which is what we'll teach you
about this morning touches on many
important areas in machine learning.
Things like probabilistic
programming, reinforcement learning,
neural nets, convex optimization,
Bayesian statistics.
And of course, many applications.
And so, that's our goal today is
to teach you about the basics.
To tell you about some
of these newer ideas.
To try to situate them in context
relative to each other and
to suggest open areas
of new research,
although I'll tell you that I
don't believe we made that slide.
So, here is the next three
parts of the tutorial.
In part two, the next part, I'll
give you the basics of variational
inference, particularly around what
are called conditionally conjugate
models and talk a little bit about
how to make variational inference
scalable with stochastic variation
inference, then Rajash will talk
about stochastic gradients of
the variational objective function.
Which via Monte Carlo, which help
us expand variations inference
to too many more types of models
than we could in the late 90s and
early 2000.
And then finally, Shakir will talk
about beyond the mean fields.
I know I haven't defined mean field
yet, but beyond the main field where
we can take those same stochastic
gradient and they enable
us to think about very complicated
and expressive variational families.
And so, this is what I just said
is the summary of this tutorial.
Here's the picture of
variational inference.
Variational inference is about
approximating difficult quantities
from complex models turning
inference into optimization and
the running theme of this tutorial
is that variational inference, and
stocastic optimization
are powerful combination.
With stocastic optimization,
we can scale variational
inference to massive datasets.
We can enable variational inference
on a wide class of difficult
models and
we can enable variational different
inference with an elaborate, and
flexible families of approximations
for those q distributions.
This is the summary.
So with that, let's begin and
talk about the simple ideas,
mean-field variational inference and
stochastic variational inference.
It's useful to have a model that
we're talking about concretely when
discussing these idea.
The motivation here is
gonna be topic modelling.
Topic modelling are models that use
posterior inference to discover
the hidden structure in big,
unstructured collections
of documents.
Unsupervised learning method and
one of the earlier examples of
variational inference
applied to a real problem.
And so, the example model that
we'll look at is latent Dirichlet
allocation or LDA and
I'll go over it quickly.
LDA, this is a document model
works based on the intuition that
documents exhibit multiple topics.
Here is an article about determining
the number of genes that
an organism needs to survive
from science magazine and
I've highlighted different words
here with different colors.
Words like computer analysis,
predictions computational blue.
Words like genes and
genomes are yellow.
Words like organisms and
life, and survivor are pink.
These are all different topics.
This article could be seen as
combining data analysis and
genetics and evolutionary biology
and the intuition behind LDA is that
if I bother to highlight every
word in this article and
you squinted at it, you'd say,
this combines those topics.
What we wanna do is we wanna build
that into a probability model.
So here is the probability model,
latent Dirichlet allocation which as
a generative process
assumes the following.
First, each topic is
a distribution over words.
So, this is gonna be like a mixture
model where the mixture components
are distributions over words.
Words like gene and DNA have high
probability in this one, and so on,
and then each document is generated
by this model by first choosing
a distribution over those topics.
Then for each word,
choosing a colored button from that
distribution over topics and
then choosing the word from
the corresponding distribution over
terms, the corresponding topic.
So, this is what's called a mixed
membership model in statistics.
It's an example of
a Bayesian model for
which we cannot compute that
normalizing constant and you
can see it as a mixture model where
each document comes from a mixture.
The mixture components
are shared across documents, but
the mixture proportions
are unique for each document.
They're drawn fresh for
each document.
I turn the page of science and
I generate an article now about data
analysis in neuroscience,
for instance.
So, this is LDA.
But more generally,
this is mixed membership modelling.
It's an example of
a class of models for
which it's difficult to
do posterior inference.
Now, what is posterior inference?
Of course, we don't get of observe
all that structure that I described
for you in explaining the model.
Really, we just get to
observe the documents.
And so, we wanna fill in all
those hidden random variables.
And so, that is a posterior
distribution here.
The probability of topics,
proportions and
assignments given the documents.
That's an example of when we're
doing posterior inference and
notice we'll get to this later.
We wanna do this with
millions of documents and
billions of latent variables.
If there's a latent variable for
every word,
we have billions of
latent variables.
So in the modelling process,
we wanna represent our
models as graphical models.
These encode assumptions about
the data by factorizing the joint
distribution of the hidden and
observed variables.
It connects to both assumptions that
we're making through the model and
algorithms for computing with
data using this model, and
it defines the posterior
through the joint.
So, here's the graphical model for
LDA.
Remember, nodes
are random variables.
Edges denote dependence
between random variables.
Shaded nodes are observed,
unshaded nodes are hidden.
And so you can think of this as a
picture of the posterior, cuz I have
observed the words of each document
and everything else is hidden.
So in this picture, the topics,
those distributions over
terms are denoted by data.
So, it's K of them.
These rectangles are plates and
denote replications,
so we have K topics.
And then for each document,
I choose a distribution over topic.
That's theta.
And then for each word in each
document, I choose a colored button.
That's Z and then I choose the word
from the corresponding topic.
So, this picture tells us what
the factorization is of a joint
distribution and
connects the algorithms.
Again, here's the posterior now for
this specific model and you can see,
it is the joint divided by the
marginal distribution of the words.
And again, we cannot compute
that denominator, so
we appeal to approximate inference.
I didn't know why
that slide was there.
Here's an example of doing inference
with that model on a large dataset
with the kind of algorithms
I'm gonna tell you about.
So with this model, we feed in two
million New York Times articles or
1.8 New York Times articles.
We look at the posterior
distribution of those distributions
over terms and we see words that
go together in coherent topics.
Words like children's school,
family, parents, stock percent,
companies, market and so on.
So, how did we get there?
How did we get from that assumption,
that model, the posterior that we
couldn't compute to
an algorithm that computed or
approximated the posterior
that we cared about?
How did we get there?
Well, in the next three sections
of the talk, I'm gonna first
define a generic class of models
that, that model is an instance of.
Derive the classical mean field
variational inference algorithm for
that generic class and then derive
the stochastic variational inference
which let us scale that
algorithm to large datasets,
but keeping in mind LDA
is our running example.
So, here is a generic
class of models.
So we have observations x,
x1 though n.
We have what are called
local variable z.
There is a z for every x and
we have a global variables beta.
The difference between local and
global variables is that the i theta
point x only depends on its local
variable z and the global variables
beta, and those criteria are denoted
in this graphical model, and
in the corresponding
factorized joint distribution.
Our goal, of course is to
compute the posterior,
the probability of beta and
z, given x.
So, let's define a few more terms.
First, the complete conditional.
What is the complete conditional?
The complete conditional is
the conditional distribution of
a latent variable, given all of
the other latent variable and
all of the observations.
So if you know the Gibbs sampler,
you know that the complete
conditional is what you sample from
when you define a Gibbs sampler.
Now, we're gonna assume in this
class of models that each complete
conditional is in
an exponential family.
So here what I've done is I've put
those complete conditionals in their
typical exponential family form,
in their natural
exponential family form.
I'm sorry, I wanna go over there,
but I just somehow
needs to be over here.
And so here, for
example is the complete conditional.
We'll start with
the global variables.
The complete conditional of beta,
given all of the local latent
variables z and the observations.
That's in some exponential family
where notice that the natural
parameter of that exponential
family is a function of
whatever it is I'm conditioning on.
That makes sense.
It's a conditional distribution,
so the natural parameter of function
of what I'm conditioning on.
And we're being general here, so
this can be any exponential family,
a gamma, multinomial, categorical,
Gaussian, whatever it might be.
The complete conditional of
the local variable, first of all,
notice it only depends on the global
variable and its data point.
And that's a function of
the independence assumptions that
this model naturally makes.
And it too is an exponential family.
An arbitrary exponential family.
So this is a restriction we're
placing on this class of models.
Now when we assume that, we can
say something about the global
parameter or
the global random variable.
From the theory around conjugacy,
here we're citing the Bernardo and
Smith Bayesian Theory book, but
this is a from the 70's I think.
From congegacy, we know that that
natural parameter of the complete
conditional of the global
variable has a particular form.
And it's the hyper parameter plus
the sum of sufficient statistics
applied to each data point and
local variable.
And so, we're gonna come back to
this form later of the natural
parameter of the complete
conditional.
Of the global variable.
So we just defined a class of models
where we have this graphical model,
where we've asserted that
each complete conditional in
an exponential family.
And that class of models actually
describes most of the models that
you might have read about,
in the 90s and
2000s in the machine
learning literature.
So Bayesian mixture models, time
series models, factorial models,
matrix factorization models,
mixed membership models like LDA,
a variety of models all
fall into that category.
You can take any of those models and
funnel them into this framework.
So, what we're gonna do is
variational inference on that
large class.
Again, here is the picture
of variational inference.
Define a q, optimize the parameter
to that q to make it
close in KL divergence to
the posterior that we care about.
This is an important slide.
So that KL divergence
is intractable.
We actually can't compute
the KL divergence.
Somebody asked me about this
in line for lanyard actually.
They said, hey,
how did the variational inference,
you can't compute the KL divergence
because it requires knowing
the posterior itself.
Which is not the typical
lanyard line conversation.
And this is the answer to that
question, if you're here Vincent.
Then this is the answer.
What we do is we work with
what's called the ELBO.
It's called the evidence
lower bound.
And it's a lower bound on log p(x)
on the problematic denominator of
the posterior.
More importantly,
maximizing the ELBO is equivalent
to minimizing the KL diversion.
Kind of easy to see.
And so
this is our objective function for
this whole talk, the ELBO.
Now you can see that
the ELBO has two terms.
The first term, so it's a function
of the variational parameters.
That makes sense, cuz
we're going to optimize with respect
to the variational parameters.
And it has two terms.
The first term is the expectation
of the log joint.
So now if you just in your mind
imagined the log joint use the chain
rule, divide it up in log prior
plus log of the likelihood.
You could see that if I
only had that term and
I was optimizing with respect to q,
I would want q to place
all of its mass on the MAP
estimate of the latent variables.
That's for the first term.
The second term of course
is the entropy of q,
minus expectation log q.
That's the entropy of q.
So while the first
remember wants me,
I'm q to all my mass on the map
estimate of the latent variables,
the second term says I actually
also want q to be diffuse.
And so these terms trade off and,
in the sense that the second
term is regularizing the first.
One caveat, the ELBO is not convex.
So it's true,
our goal is to optimize this, but
it's also true that this
is not a convex function.
So, we're gonna find a local
optimum of the ELBO.
So that's our goal,
to optimize the ELBO.
We still need to, wow, okay.
We still need to
specify the form of q.
We still need to specify
what is this q of z, and
beta, that we're gonna optimize.
And that's where another
important idea comes in,
the mean-field family.
Well, you've probably heard of
mean-field variational inference,
it's about the family that we're
optimizing with respect to.
So the mean-field family says,
that all the latent variables
are independent and governed by
their own variational parameter.
So here I have q of beta and z.
Has variational parameters,
lambda and
phi, where we have q of
beta governed by lambda and
then independently,
q of z is governed by its own phi.
So I might have 10
million latent variables.
Each one has its own variational
parameter and I'm tweaking all of
those parameters, to make the
corresponding distribution close to
the exact posterior.
Furthermore, to fully specify that
family, each factor is gonna be in
the same family as the models
complete conditional.
So, if p of beta given z and x as
a gamma, then Q of beta is gonna be
a gamma with a phi parameter
lambda that I can control.
When I show this to statisticians
they think it's crazy, because it's
a bunch of disconnected variables
each with their own parameter.
And there's no data in there so
how are we estimating it?
The idea is that through the ELBO,
through this optimization function,
through the convergence,
we are connecting this family to
the data and
the posterior that we care about.
So that's how it all works,
that's the full setup.
We then optimize the ELBO.
The ELBO defined in terms of
these variational parameters.
And the nice result of Geramani and
Beal from 2001 is that,
if we iteratively optimize each
parameter in turn holding the other
parameters fixed, then they have
this nice coordinate update.
Lambda is the expectation
of eta of Z and x.
And phi is the expectation
of eta of beta and x.
And the mean field assumption
ensures, that the right
hand side of each update is
independent of the left hand side.
And so this is how varitional
inference in the 90s
and 2000s worked.
We set up variational parameters,
and then we marched down those
variational parameters,
iteratively updating each one.
That gets us to a local
optimum of the ELBO.
And notice the relationship
to Gibb sampling.
In Gibb sampling we iteratively
sample from these distributions.
In variational inference,
we set these parameters equal to
the expectation of their
natural parameters.
Now.
Let's go back to LDA very quickly,
cuz I'm trying to be
sensitive about the time of.
So in LDA, mean field family
says everything's independent.
The topic proportions,
all the topic assignments.
And from that, we can run coordinate
descent variational inference.
Take our article,
look at its topic proportions.
So that's an example of
what we would do with
a fitted variational parameter.
We would take it and then look at
it, just to explore the corpus.
And then, we can look at,
we can see this article exhibits
only a handful of topics.
We can look at the most frequent
words from the most frequent topics.
And we see that they, again
through the variational parameters
give us something interpretable.
And so this is classical
variational inference.
In a nutshell.
We start with our data and
a model, and we repeatedly update
each variational parameter using
these coordinate ascent updates,
until the ELBO has converged.
Again, that recipe gives you
variational inference for
a huge class of models, or
for a large class of models.
For a huge class of models,
Rajes will talk about it.
There's a problem though.
Classical variational
inference's inefficient.
L let's take LBA as an example.
We start out with random topics,
garbage topics, that have no
meaning, and then we pain stakingly
analyze every article according to
those topics cuz we have to,
that's what the recipe dictates.
We have to march through all of our
latent variables and we have laying
variables for every document, before
we can update the topics again.
This can't handle massive data and
that's where stochastic
variational comes in.
Stochastic variational inference,
scales variational inference
up to massive data, and
only uses the mathematics that we
had in this first part of the talk.
This is the cartoon of stochastic
variational inference.
Where instead of marching through
the whole data set before updating
my topics, I iterively sub-sample
a small piece of the data,
infer its local hidden structure,
update an idea of the global
hidden structure and repeat.
And going through this over and
over again,
give us very fast
convergences of the ELBO.
So here's another important
idea from this tutorial.
Stochastic optimization.
And that's the key idea, that turns
classical variational inference into
stochastic variational inference.
So stochastic optimization,
this guy, his name is Herb Robins He
invented stochastic optimization,
also empirical base, also bandits.
And he did this in the 60s.
So whatever he smoked,
you wanna smoke it too.
>> [LAUGH]
>> What's
the idea behind
stochastic optimization?
This is Robbins and Munro, 1951.
The idea's that we replace
the gradient in an optimization,
with a cheaper noisy
estimate of that gradient.
This is guaranteed to
converge to a local optimum,
in a objective like the ELBO.
And this single idea really has
enabled modern machine learning.
Why are we speaking to however
many hundred of people of that
variational inference?
Because of stochastic optimization.
I feel like we owe.
Stochastic Optimization to
the success of our field.
And the idea is very simple.
When I teach Stochastic
Optimization, I tell the story that
Tamara Wants to go from here,
from Barcelona to Berlin.
How far is Berlin?
Anybody know?
Okay, I'm gonna,
let's say a thousand kilometers.
I don't know how far it is.
She wants to go to Berlin and
everybody's drunk, okay?
Here in Barcelona everybody's drunk,
but
really all over Europe
everybody's drunk.
All right so, Tamara wants to
go to Berlin, everybody's drunk,
remember I'm explaining
stochastic optimization.
What does she do?
She asks Shakir, I want to go
to Berlin and everybody's drunk,
she says to Shakir,
how do I get to Berlin?
Shakir points in some random
direction and Annie falls over.
A normal person would
ask somebody else,
but not according to
stochastic optimization.
Tamara should walk 500 km in
whatever direction Shakir pointed,
all right?
She's in the middle of
Europe somewhere let's hope,
not in the middle of the ocean,
and everybody's still drunk, and
she asks Thomas Hoffman,
hey, how do I get to Berlin?
He's German,
she thinks maybe he'll know.
But he's drunk too.
And he points in some
random direction.
She walks 250 miles
in that direction.
She runs into Andrew Ing.
He's drunk.
She runs into all kinds of people.
They're all drunk.
They all point in some
random direction.
If she takes smaller and smaller
step sizes on her way to Berlin,
you can kind of imagine.
And if we were to
magically revive Shakir and
ask him where Berlin is, he would,
on average, point exactly at Berlin,
then Tamara will eventually
get to Berlin, okay?
And it works just like that.
That is Stochastic optimization.
In mathematics, with noisy
gradients, I just follow if
that hatted gradient
represents the noisy gradient.
If I follow the noisy gradient
with a decreasing step size,
rho t is the step size,
then I will get to an optimum.
And this requires two things,
it requires unbiased gradients,
that the expectation
of the noisy gradient,
that there's a lot of expectations
floating around here.
That's an expectation with
respect to this random gradient.
That that expectation,
if that is unbiased,
meaning the expectation of the noisy
gradient equals the true gradient,
if I could revive Shakir he
would point right at Berlin.
We need that for
this to work in 1951.
And two, we need the step size
sequence row T to follow what
are called the RobbinsMonro
condition.
And those say that we need to
be able to get to Berlin but
we need to slow down at a rate such
that we will eventually get there,
even though we have noisy gradients.
Now, lately in machine learning,
we've played with those
Robbins-Monro conditions, right,
innovations like and play with that.
But this is the idea
in this old paper.
Okay, and this is gonna be the key
idea through out this talk, so
cast the compromisation.
Okay, so in this first setting of
conditionally conjugate models,
the natural gradient of
the ELBO the natural gradients,
this type of gradient
looks like that.
It's alpha plus the sum of these
expected sufficient statistics
minus lambda.
And these expected sufficient
statistics are taken with respect to
the optimum local parameters.
So therefore we can construct
a noisy gradient by sampling
a datapoint at random and
then computing this scaled
version of that natural gradient.
All right,
this is a good noisy gradient.
Because you can probably see, its
expectation is the exact gradient
because I'm choosing a data
point uniformly at random.
By the way, this is a vanilla
application of stochastic
optimization here.
Its expectation is the exact
gradient, it's unbiased.
And it's cheap, it only depends
on the optimized parameters of
one of the data points, okay?
So rather than marching through all
of the documents to get this noisy
gradient, I just plot one document,
and
I find how it exhibits the local
structure, and then proceed.
Okay, and that gives us
stochastic variational inference,
which looks like this.
I'm getting signs that I'm
running out of time, so
I'm gonna skip this slide.
But more importantly,
it looks like this. Right?
I subsample them from my data.
I Infer its local structure.
In other words, I optimize its
local variational parameter.
I then update the global structure
by updating this natural,
this scaled natural gradient,
by updating the global
variational parameter according
to this scaled natural gradient.
And then I repeat, all right?
So for LDA how does this look?
Sample one document.
Estimate how it
exhibits the topics and
then update the global topics
based on those estimates.
Why is this a good idea?
Here's a picture.
So in the top part of this plot,
we have on the X axis,
document seen at a log scale.
So, here I'm fitting an LDA model,
and this is how many documents,
I've had to do some kind of
inference about on the X axis.
And the Y axis is perplexity,
it's a measure of model fitness,
where lower numbers are better.
All right, so
first look at this line, batch 98k.
This is 100,000 documents.
This is about what we could do with
the classical mean field variation
inference, and you can see that
before we even get one point on this
estimate of model fitness, we have
to have observed 100,000 documents.
The whole collection and
then at each iteration,
we process the whole collection.
But with stochastic variational
inference we can analyze the whole
document collection,
3.5 million, and
by the time we've processed the same
amount of documents that we
processed in just one iteration of
batch inference, what's called batch
inference, we're already at
a much better place, okay?
And more importantly, this is what
lets us do things like estimate
topics from millions of
New York Times articles on a laptop.
And again, this is general for
that whole class of conditionally
conjugate models, all right?
So now you can scale up any of these
models from the 90s and 2000s,
you can scale them up to
very large data sets using
Stochastic variational inference.
Okay, that's how we
got these pictures.
All right.
So,
that is kind of where things
were a couple of years ago, and
now I'll turn it over to Rajesh.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> All right, thanks Dave.
I'm gonna get into,
did we really hit that promise.
We talked about how
we have a question.
Have some knowledge.
Want to use probability models
to express that knowledge.
Take our data, find the patterns,
and then predict and explore.
Well, I'd say that for conditionally
conjugate models, we saw a pretty
good way to do this, stochastic
variational inference scales.
It works for
this pretty large class of models.
But one question we might have is,
what about the general case?
So to get into this, let's go over
these variational inference recipe.
So like if you sit down with
a model like what you do?
So here we have our
little tired Phd student,
may be jet-lagged Phd student today.
He's thought of a model which is
a joint distribution over the latent
variable Z and data X.
The next thing that happens
is you need to choose
a variational approximation,
which is a distribution
over the latent variables with
some free parameters, nu.
Then we get an objective.
This objective is
the evidence lower bound.
It is a function of nu.
And part of the dependence
of nu comes from the actual,
dependence on nu comes
form the expectation.
And so to optimize this,
we need to take that expectation.
So for example, we can get
a function that looks something like
this after we take the expectation.
It's explicitly in terms of nu and
to optimize this,
we can take our standard approach.
We compute its gradient and
we optimize with some
form of gradient ascent.
So this recipe is
fairly straightforward.
I just work from the outside in and
then put it into an optimizer and
we can summarize it with
this picture right here.
We have a model,
I have variational approximation,
compute the expectation,
take a derivative and then optimize.
But let's see how this works for
a fairly simple model.
So, this model is
Bayesian Logistic Regression.
If you're familiar with
the logistic regression
which is a binary labeled
prediction problem.
The Bayesian version puts a prior
on the regression coefficient.
So here, X are the covariance,
Y are the binary labels,
Z is the regression coefficient and
that has a normal zero one prior.
Let's make this even simpler so
we can actually see what happens.
Let's assume we only
have a single data point.
Let's also assume our
covariants are scalar, and
let's choose our approximating
family to be a normal distribution.
It's nice.
We have some properties
we can exploit.
And let's write down the evidence
lower bound for this.
So to follow the recipe,
now that we have that lower bound.
We have to compute that integral,
we have to take the expectation.
And so the first step,
we just write it out.
For the next step, we can use
our properties for Gaussian
distributions, you now expand the
first term to get the expectation
of the square and the second term is
the anthropy up to some constant C.
Next, we can expand out
the likelihood of the data, so
that just the vernuli likelihood
of a single data point.
We can take the expectation on
the first term because you know, Z,
you know the expectation of the
Gaussian running variable but for
that last term, we're stuck.
We can analytically take that
expectation, the dependence on,
we'd like to do it because we wanna
make the dependence on parameters
explicit so
we can use gradients to optimize.
And so, we need something else.
So there are some options for this.
We can further bound that object.
We can analyze that function.
Find the lower bound and
we get a consistent objective.
That is very model specific because
that function is going to look
different for
different kinds of models.
And you can also have
more general things, but
these also still require
computations around the model.
And while we think that hey,
there's one example,
let's really work on that example so
this might be okay.
But here's a different
list of models, and
all these models are nonconjugate.
Meaning that they don't fall
into the class that Dave
mentioned earlier.
So you know we have nonlinear
time series models,
we have models with attention,
regression models.
Even fancier versions
of the topic model,
deep exponential families,
Bayesian neural networks.
The models before were really very
limited because they were defined
with conjugacy in mind.
Now that you're free,
this list can go on for,
we're still creating them.
But because of that we really
need a solution that doesn't
entail model-specific work.
Because this kind of derivation
really slows down the process
of developing these models and
figuring out what is
the right tool for your data.
And what we want is
summarized in this picture.
We wanna be able to take any model,
massive data, some reasonable
facts about the variational families
that were introduced earlier.
Feed it into this
computational engine,
we'll call black box
variational inference, and
get a posterior distribution or
approximation of it.
So, what's the problem in
the classical variational
inference recipe that really
stops this from happening?
It's really this computation
of this integral to make
the elbow explicit in terms of
the variational parameters do.
And that's why it's
highlighted in red.
So, red is like a stoplight.
But if we switch the order
of these two steps, so
before computing the expectation,
we compute the gradient then try
to approximate the expectation.
We might find success and
why might this work.
The same reason we saw earlier,
stochastic optimization.
But to do this,
we'll need a general way to
compute gradients of expectations.
So I'm going to go over this
slide carefully because a lot of
what I'll talk about in
the next parts relies on this.
So imagine the term
inside the elbow,
which is a function
of latent variables.
And the variational parameters.
That's log p(x,z) minus
the variational distribution.
To compute its gradient without
taking the expectation first,
we first write in integration form.
We make the assumption that swap
the integration in differentiation.
Which is true for
a relatively general case.
This next line here is just the
product rule, so we differentiate
the first term and then we
differentiate the second term.
The third line,
we rewrite the gradient with
respect to mu of q using something
called the log derivative trick.
And what this lets us do is it
let's us introduce the density
into both terms so we can rewrite
this object as an expectation.
And this is really the tool that'll
make the rest of the talk work.
So a roadmap, I'm going to cover
two kinds of gradient estimators
that are built from that
differentiation rule.
Score function gradient and
pathways gradient.
And lastly, I'm gonna talk about how
to make inference with data large
even faster than we saw with So
score function
gradients of the ELBO.
So the very first term here
we have just written down our
differentiation rule
we derived earlier.
To simplify this,
we see that the second term Is
just the score function hence how
the score function estimator gets
its name, has expectate zero.
We get the form of the gradient
given the model probability.
The probability variational
approximation times
the square function.
This estimator, we call
the square function estimator.
But also has other names likelihood
ratio from the Monte Carlo
literature or reinforce from
reinforcement learning.
But how do I use this,
now that the gradients expectation,
what's the next step?
Really the next step
is once an object is an expectation
with a distribution that I know,
I can use Monte Carlo to construct
noisy, unbiased gradients.
So, specifically,
we can sample from Q and we can take
the average of over those samples of
the quantity inside the expectation.
As we saw earlier, if you have
unbiased stochastic gradients,
we can get an algorithm that
will converge to a local optima.
And let's look at that algorithm.
This algorithm is just Basic
Black Box Variational Inference.
What you do is you draw a bunch of
samples from your approximation,
you choose a learning rate from
the roman numeral sequence.
And you update your current
parameters with the learning rate
times the Monte Carlos
to cast the gradient
that we defined on the previous
slide and then that's really it.
Theoretically this would work
if you had enough computation.
So what are the requirements for
inference?
Do we really meet these
black box criteria?
Well, if we look at our formula,
we need to be able to sample from
the variational approximation.
We choose that, so and
it's not related to the model so
we have some flexibility there.
We need to be evaluate
the score function.
Again, we choose q,
we can derive that once,
put it in a table and reuse it.
And we need to be able to evaluate
the log probability of the model
which is the same as
specifying the model itself.
And we need the probability of
the variational approximation too.
The key thing here is really this,
there's no model specific work.
Our criteria are really satisfied.
All I have to do is write
down the joint distribution.
And so
it really does look like this.
I have a bunch of facts about about
my variational approximation,
how to sample it,
it's score function, it's density.
I can take in my model which is in
the form of this joint distribution.
I can take in data and I can
get an approximate posterior by
running that algorithm
I just showed.
But, that algorithm
doesn't work directly.
Variance really can be a problem.
So when you do
stochastic optimization,
your gradients are noisy.
The more noise you have
in those gradients,
the slower the optimization process.
This wasn't really a problem in
the classical setup because you took
the expectation first,
then took the derivative.
You're noise free.
And now that we're sampling,
you can get quite high variants.
And this picture really gives
some intuition around that.
So this is just the score function
of a Gaussian distribution, and
this is the PDF of
a Gaussian distribution.
Intuitively, sampling rare
values can lead to large scores.
Which can give you high variance,
and
this is a problem
we need to address.
One solution for
this are control variance.
The idea behind a control variance
that comes from Monte Carlo
estimation is to replace a function
that we're trying to compute its
expectation of with another function
that has the same expectation but
possibly lower variance.
And one general way to
create that function,
so hat f,
is to take the original function and
subtract from it something
that has expectation zero.
So take a general function h,
and subtract its expectation.
It has expectation zero.
And in this case, you know,
h is the control variable,
it's the function of our choice.
And you can choose this scaling
factor here to minimize
the variance.
So this picture kinda
depicts what's happening.
So again, in red,
I have a Gaussian distribution.
In blue, I have a function f, whose
expectation I'm trying to estimate.
It's x plus x squared.
Let's say that I use X squared
as a control variate using
the fact that I know what
the expectation of X squared is for
Gaussian distribution.
The function F hat gets
changed from this blue version
to this green version,
which has lower variability.
If I take this all the way and
say that h is equal to F.
I'll actually get something
that has zero variance.
We can see this from this formula
here where the f will cancel and
you'll actually just get the f
hat is equal to the expectation,
which is what we're looking for.
But we need a way to specify h.
We really want to maintain our
black box criteria because we're
after some level of
genericness in your inference.
And what that means is we need a
function that has known expectation
for a broad class of models.
And we saw one already.
So, if we set h to be the score
function, we saw previously
that this thing has expectation
zero for a large number of q.
And because of that,
we can directly use it as a control
variate to reduce the variance.
There are a lot of other techniques
from Monte Carlo that can help here
and that are still being applied
to variational inference.
Things like importance sampling,
quasi Monte Carlo and
Rao-Blackwellization which is
a kind of marginalization.
And I'm coming back to this model
list with the algorithm we have,
we can actually run inference for
all these models and
even many more that we have yet
to think of.
And I think that the nice point
to make here is that rather than
designing models based on inference,
we can design them based
on the data we have and for
the problem that we're trying to
solve and tailor it to that problem.
So we have a current set of black
box assumptions which are sampling
from q, it's core function and
evaluating densities.
Can we make additional assumptions
that make inference easier or
faster?
Unless we get us to the second
estimator for various and
inference call
the pathways estimator.
So, the two assumptions we'll
make are the following.
The first assumption will be that
for our variational approximation.
So these coming from our variational
approximation, right there.
We can rewrite it in terms of a
noise source that's parameter-free.
What that means is given
some epsilon that comes
from a distribution s with no
parameters, so not dependent on new.
We can then transform that
noise source with a function
that depends on the parameters to
get a random variable that has
the same distribution
as the original.
So that's a lot, but we're familiar
with several examples to this.
One simple one is if you take
a normal distribution and say,
I want a normal with some mean and
some variance.
One way to do this is to draw
from the standard normal.
So there are no parameters here,
it's zero and one and
then just do a location scale
transformation of that.
So multiply by the standard
deviation and then add the mean.
The second assumption that we'll
make are that the model and
the variational approximation
are differentiable with respect to
the latent variables and
this smoothness assumption
will buy us something,
we'll see in the next slides.
So to compute the gradients in this
way, recall our original gradient
formula which is the score function
times log p minus log q times this
derivative and we can rewrite this
using our transformation rule.
And when we do that, we get a very
similar form, except now we have
the score function with respect to
this parameter free distribution.
We have the elbow of
the transformation and
we have the gradient of the
transformed elbow with respect to
its parameters.
One thing to note here is like
in the score function estimator,
the second term was zero.
But in this case, because the noise
distribution does not depend on
the parameters, it's zero.
So, we can simplify this.
So we have the second term,
just expanding it out here.
We can expanding out here and
using the chain rule.
We get the derivative of the model
times the chain rule term minus
the score function and we can get
rid of the score function term
using the same fact we used earlier,
and this is also known as
the reparameterization gradient
if you're familiar with that.
So, why would we want to do this?
We limited the class of models and
made assumptions that
are a little bit, maybe odd, but
it really does buy us something.
So here, we have the variance of
the gradient on the y-axis and
on the x-axis and this is just
the number of Monte Carlo
samples we're taking,
to estimate that.
The basic estimator describe
has variance that's orders of
magnitude larger than this
pathwise estimator and
it's also larger than using
that score function estimator.
It's also smaller than using
the score function estimator with
a control variant and this is why
this approach is really popular.
So comparing between the two,
we have that the score function
estimator differentiates the density
while the pathwise estimator
differentiates the function and
these are really
the only two options.
Because if you remember what
that integral looks like,
it's the integral of sum
density times sum function.
The score function one
works pretty generally.
It works for
a broad class of approximations.
We don't need it to be
parameterizable, but
variance is really a big problem.
And so, what the pathwise estimator
is all about is making this set
of assumptions.
So differentiable models and
some amount of reparameterization to
get generally better
behaved variance, so
you can deploy it on
new models more easily.
So, the last thing I'm gonna talk
about is amortized inference.
So, recall the hierarchical model
that Dave covered in his section.
In this model, you have a global
latent variable which is beta,
which is shared across data.
You have a local variable z and
you have data xi, and
this local variables are one for
each data point, and
that's why they're in the box.
The join distribution
has this form here,
which is a product across
those local factors.
And as we saw earlier,
we can define a main field very
strong approximation for this and
we can do stochastic variational
inference, but there is a problem
with that stochastic variational
inference in this setup.
Mainly, the expectations that we
require are no longer tractable.
It's the same problem we saw earlier
when we were trying to compute that
integral, you just can't get
a nice analytic form for it.
So instead,
we need to do something else.
We could do the same trick of doing
stochastic optimization inside
an inner loop, but
now the stochastic variational
inference algorithm would get slow.
Because instead of just writing the
equation for an expectation, you're
gonna run an optimization algorithm
for each data point you get.
And so, the idea here is
to learn a mapping that
goes from a data point to its
local variational parameters.
And so, let's see how to do that.
And so for the top line,
we have the evidence lower bound for
a general hierarchical model.
This has the terms of
just the data terms and
it has the entropy part,
which I expanded
just to see what's happening for
the per data variational parameters.
So the way that amortizing it
works with an inference network
is to say that instead of
having just the phi i for
each single data point,
you can make that phi i
to be a function of xi with some
new variational parameters theta.
So, why this is called amortized
is because the variational
parameters that used to be one for
each data point have gotten replaced
with parameters to a function that
are shared across data points.
And making this change allows us
to apply these black box inference
techniques directly to get something
that scales across data and
is general for
a broad class of models, and
that's what this algorithm
does here where we can sample
a global latent variable from
its variation approximation.
We sample a data point.
We can sample a local latent
variable given its parameters and
then we just use stochastic
optimization to update both
the variational approximation
on the global variables, and
the parameters for the inference
network on the local variables,
and that's what these
two updates are.
So, this is really a computational
and statistical tradeoff.
What I mean by that is by choosing
the amortized family, we've
shrunken the class of variational
approximations and the size
of how much we shrunk it by depends
on the complexity of the function.
So, one way to think about this
is imagine just the best case
where there are some optimal values
of phi in each data point and
f perfectly predicts that.
That is the best thing it can do and
that's why it's a smaller
class than the original.
So, let's look at
an example of issues.
So, there's a popular model called
the variational autoencoder.
What is does from
the generative standpoint,
it puts a prior over a vector
of random variables.
That's simple,
it's just normal zero, one.
And it generates the data with say,
a normal distribution with functions
that are parameterized by
the global variables and
taken as input
the locally variable and
both these functions are generally
some form of deep networks.
To do inference in this,
we use our inference network.
So we specify a mean-field
approximation where
the parameters of that
approximation, in this case,
normal distribution,
come from functions of the data.
So we have a mean parameter
coming from the data and
we have a variance parameter
coming from the data.
And the picture on the left
really describes this process.
So the model is generative in the
sense that you take latent variable,
you pass it through
a set of deep functions.
And then, you have a likelihood
function where you can sample data.
And on inference this
process is reversed.
We take data, we pass it
through these two deep networks
to get parameters for
the variational approximators and
that's the distribution up here And
this really works, so here's
some results that are produced
by variational autoencoders.
The top just is a measure
of model fitness.
And the variational
autoencoder does well.
And these other pictures are,
we have some simulation results.
You know how well can you generate
for faces or house numbers.
And the last one is a different task
where we have our original data.
We have corrupted that data so
this is what the model sees.
And we tried to do
inference to recover
the original values based
on what the model thinks.
And this is just a postulate
calculation also.
So in the last part of my segment,
I'm gonna go over
some rules of thumb.
And the first rules of thumb, I
think that are important are how to
choose between these two
kinds of estimators.
If your model is differentiable, I
think the first thing you do is try
out a variational approximation
that's reparameterizable.
And that's because, variance is
an issue in the other case and
it's pretty well behaved for
this estimator.
If your model is not differentiable,
the process is a little bit slower.
You're gonna use the score
function estimator,
because that's all you can use.
And you should use it with
the control variates right away.
But I think you'll also have
to add further variance
reductions based on
experimental evidence.
What I mean by that is
you'll plot your evidence.
You'll plot the variance
of the gradients,
you'll see how much
progress you're making.
If you're making too little
progress, you'll probably have to
adapt one of the other techniques
that I listed earlier.
And there's some more general advice
I think that is important for
optimizing these problems, too.
Which is, don't use
the Robbins-Monro sequences,
use something like RMSProp and
AdaGrad, which do coordinate
specific learning rates.
There's something
called annealing which
bounces the cause between
the regularization term the entropy
that they talked about
in the likelihood,
which can help getting stock
in local optimal early on.
And from a conversational stand
points, the algorithms we describe
there really embarrassingly
parallel across samples.
And so, implementing it that way can
make the entire inference
process much faster.
For software,
there are two different kinds
of systems that are useful here.
The first kind of system are systems
that have variational inference
built into it and these are
probabilistic for any languages and
there are a lot of them.
There's Venture,
WebPPL, Edward, PyMC3.
And what these are really good for,
they're good for
trying out just a broad
class of models.
The second set of tools
are just math libraries.
They let you do differentiation,
they provide other utilities,
maybe like log probabilities.
And what they're useful for
is getting a faster implementation
of an individual model, because you
can take advantage of structure in
that model in your implementation.
And thanks.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> And
I'd like to take you through a bit
more of the more recent work
that's happened in variational
inference in the past few years.
And to get to this point,
we've needed a number of
different ingredients.
And we began with Dave, who
introduced us to the principles of
probabilistic modelling, the
principles of variational inference.
And how we can really scale
our models using stochastic
optimisation.
And Rajesh just introduced as to
black-box variational inference
methods and how we can automate the
process of variational inference.
How we can extend them to
non-conjugate models, use
Monte Carlo gradients estimators and
use amortized variational inference.
And without us knowing it,
we have now been empowered
to answer one of the key questions
in variational inference.
Which is how do you
choose that variable q?
How can you get the best
distribution possible?
And sort of for the next 30 minutes,
we're just gonna explore
different ways of doing that.
So this was the variational
inference picture that we
showed in the beginning.
You need to find the best
approximation to the true posterior
distribution, p of z given x.
And what we needed to do was specify
some family of distributions
which we called q, what some
variational parameters knew.
And up to this point,
everything that we need was called
the mean field approximation or
what would sometimes called
the fully factorized approximation.
So in my little cartoon image here,
we have three dimensions
of a latent variable Zed.
And the latent variables have
no connections between them.
So we assume they are independent
Gaussians for example.
And once we make that assumption,
we can then optimize
our variation low bound
using the Monte Carlo techniques
that Rajesh just described.
And so, the question is,
is this a good idea?
So the way we'll do that is
by exploring some real world
posteriors.
So, Rajesh just described to you
what was this model, a deep latent
Gaussian model, it consists of
a latent variable of Gaussian.
And then it goes through
some deep network and
the example we're looking at is
a two fully connected hinted layer.
And then we have modelling MS
digits where we'll use the newly
distribution at the end.
And these two plots are a plot for
one of these digits.
It's number five in this case and
we're looking at the true posterior
distribution, which is the grey.
And there are two plots,
it's the same posterior distribution
at different zoom levels.
And so there are some interesting
things to look at and to
learn from this plot already, just
in two dimensional latent variables.
One is that this posterior
looks like Gaussian, so
a Gaussian could do quite well, but
it has a slight bit of correlation.
There's a little bit of a tilt in
that grey contour at the back,
ignore the blue curve.
If we use the mean
field approximation,
then we will only have axis-aligned
Gaussian, which means we will never
be able to model even that
small amount of correlation.
So a conclusion already from simple
kind of plots like this is that
the mean-field or
fully factorized assumption
usually will not be sufficient.
So let's look at
a few other diagrams.
So here are a few
other of the digits.
There are four plots, and
each of them has four sub-plots.
But they're all, again,
the same posterior distribution
at different zoom levels.
And we're gonna look, focus on
the gray contours in the end.
And we see a lot of interesting
things in the first one,
there can be very strong dependency,
strong correlation between
the distributions.
Sort of in the second one,
the distributions can
look somewhat spherical but
they aren't quite Gaussian.
In the third one you have
distributions that are somewhat
multi modal with some way
density connecting the two
parts of the mode.
And in the other part you can have
some very heavy tail with very sharp
cut offs.
And so
from here we take the lesson that
the kind of posterior distributions
that we see in the real world
have complex dependencies.
They're typically non-Gaussian and
they might have multiple modes.
And these are the three kinds of
things that we're
gonna try to look for.
So this means that we're gonna
have two high-level goals.
We wanna build to these very
rich posterior distributions.
Distributions that are non-Gaussian,
can have complex dependencies and
can be multimodal.
But at the same time, everything
that we that we just learned from
Rajesh and Dave about maintaining
computational complexity,
we need to keep that and
scalability.
So, that sort of means that
what we have is a spectrum
of different approaches.
On one end, we have the true
posterior distribution, which is
the best thing we can do but the
true posterior is unavailable to us.
And on the other end we have
the mean-field approximation
which is the least expressive,
the simplest thing we could do.
And in between, there lies a whole
range of ideas that we can explore.
And everything you know
about building models
can now be applied here.
Cuz the process and
the problem of designing good
posterior approximations is
going to be exactly the same as
the way we think about
building models themselves.
And everything we know we're going
to use in somewhat different way.
So the first way to think about this
is how can you improve your fully
factorized approximation and
introduce some structure.
So, this would call
the structured mean field, and
in the example that I have, instead
of having no dependencies between
the individual dimensions
of the later variable.
I'll have a dependency between
z1 and z2, and z2 and z3.
So a structured mean field is any
kind of posterior approximation,
where we introduce some form of
dependency within the approximation.
And this can be very general.
So the first and simplest way
of introducing some dependency
is to improve that diagonal
Gaussian approximation that we use.
And that means we'll just
use a correlated Gaussian.
A correlated Gaussian is
a distribution with some variational
parameters mu, and these variational
parameters are the mean and
the variance of that Gaussian.
And now all the dependency structure
lives within the covariance.
And so we can think about
different covariance models
that we have available.
And the things we can do is start
with the mean field, which includes
the diagonal Gaussian or
we can add a rank one term to that,
which will allow us to capture
one degree of correlation.
Or we can continue to add a few
more dimensions of higher rank
up until we reach the focal
variance Gaussian.
And so this is a little plot just
to give you an indication of,
what can happen by building better
models and using better inference.
So the highest plot
is factor analysis.
The simplest model, it is
a linear latent Gaussian model,
with a factorized
posterior distribution.
You get some value
which is quite high.
And once we move to
a nonlinear model,
nonlinear models can be much more
powerful and we can make significant
gains in our understanding and
explanation of the data.
But using the wake-sleep algorithm
doesn't use a very
unified objective.
If we use variational inference,
that gives us the principles we
are deriving a unified objective
function, even with the mean
field we can still do better.
And if we do a Rank-1 approximation,
we can do better still.
And so this is sort of the lesson
of building better posterior
distributions.
There are two limitations
of this kind of thinking.
One is that, as we move from
the mean-field to rank 1,
we have a linear time computation.
It is linear in the number of
latent variables that we have.
But once you move to these higher
order approximation covariance
models, we move from something that
was linear in the number of latent
variables to something that is cubic
in the number of latent variables.
And this cubic cost is something
that will not be acceptable to us.
So we cannot actually
use this model.
The other limitation is that these
posteriors will always be Gaussian.
And this is one of the things
that we did not want to have.
So what can we do better?
So to move beyond the Gaussian,
the simplest thing to do is to use
one of the first models you probably
ever learned about, which was
the non-linear autoregressive model.
And we can use that to build
posterior distributions.
So in this example,
let's look at dimension z4.
z4 is dependent on all the other
latent variables that came
before it, z3, z2, and z1.
We introduce an ordering
on these latent variables.
And each of these
connections between z4 can,
in this case,
be a deep neural network.
So this can be very flexible.
Each of the conditional
distributions will be Gaussian, but
the joint distribution between
all of them is most certainly not
a Gaussian.
So this can be a very
good approximation.
So to give you an idea of exactly
what can be done, on the bar plot,
these are results on
the M list data set.
So in the VAE algorithm
that we looked at before,
using a mean field approximation,
we can get around 86 knots.
This is a really good number.
But when we use the best model and
we use this kind of non-linear
autoregressive posterior that can
induce these complex dependencies,
we can gain five knots.
I don't think I can explain to
how much five knots is, but
that's a lot.
And if we look at sort of
the samples that we can generate,
you can see from something very
blurry from in the VAE, we now get
much more structure, diversity of
colors and a bit more coherence.
They're not perfect images,
of course, and
the most modern work can
do much better than this.
But this is sort of
the understanding of what better
posteriors mean.
Again I said the joint
distribution is non-Gaussian.
And because of this autoregressive
structure, this maintains
the complexity which is linear in
the number of latent variables.
So we can move beyond that.
So since we can use the non-linear
autoregressive model, what other
models can we use as potential
approximate posterior distributions?
One popular approach might
be to use a mixture model,
which is a very good idea.
Or we can start with the mean
field approximation and
we can use some form
of binding function.
For example, this function C to
introduce some dependencies.
And if you look at all
the models that you will use and
think about ways of building these
better posterior distributions,
a recipe will emerge.
And what it suggests to us is that
we should try to introduce some new
variables into our approximations.
And we'll use these new variables
in some way to induce dependencies.
And every new variable
that we introduce,
we'll have to think about ways to
make sure that the approximation
is still tractable and efficient.
And so we're going to look at
exploring this in much more detail.
So here's the general recipe for
the rest of this part.
Is we're going to introduce some new
variables, and I'll call them omega.
These new variables
are going to help us.
They are going to be something we
can play around to actually build
a much richer approximation.
So while we might be interested
in this distribution queue of z
given mu, we're going to form this
new joint distribution, q of z,
comma omega given u.
We should go the integral but
we're gonna try and
work with the joint instead, which
will help us do the tractability.
So because we're gonna
now work with this joint,
the bound that we already had might
not actually work, and we'll have to
think about how we can actually
modify our bound in some way.
Usually this likelihood term
will be okay to handle, but
the entropy term will be
something difficult, and
that's one of the things we'll
think about quite a bit.
And at all points, we'll always be
thinking about the computation,
what it actually means,
what the implications, and
to ensure that we are linear in
the number of latent variables.
So there are two general approaches
that we're gonna look at.
One approach will be the change
of variables method.
I'm gonna explore some techniques
on the various different names.
Like normalizing flows, and look at
how invertible transformations and
functions can play a role here.
And the other approach will be
called auxiliary variable methods,
and we'll look at ways of
building entropy bounds,
and using other ways of
Monte Carlo sampling.
So the first way are these change of
variable methods, and this is also
one of the first things you learned
in introductory probability, which
was the rule for change of variables
of a probability distribution.
So we can start with
a simple distribution, q0,
assume it's a Gaussian, for example.
And if we take samples from
their distribution, and
we transform them through
some invertible function,
then we can know
the distribution at the end.
Because we can apply the rule for
change of variables.
Which will involve taking
the original distribution and
multiplying it by
the determinant of its Jacobean.
So here's the cartoon
that gives us that image.
We started this distribution
q0 which is a Gaussian.
And we transform it through
this nonlinear function f.
The function f must be invertible.
But once we get to the end,
that function will transform
the density and give us something
a bit more complicated.
And we can do this multiple times.
We can apply as many functions
as we like to try and
make the distribution as
complicated as we need to be.
And there are two
important properties
of this kind of a process.
The first one is that
sampling is very easy.
That if we need to generate a sample
from the final distribution
at time step t, we generate a sample
from our independent Gaussian and
we just push those samples through
the sequence of functions.
And what comes out at the end will
be a sample from this complicated
distribution.
And that sample is what we need to
do the optimization that described.
The second thing that we need
to do is to be able to compute
the entropy, this term that
was always in our bound.
And the entropy is also
very easy to compute,
because we just need to take
the log of this transformation.
So it'll just be the log of the
initial distribution which we always
know, and the log determinant of
the Jacobean which we can always
compute, because we get to
this design this function f.
And so
we call this a normalizing flow,
because this initial
distribution flows through this
sequence of distributions
at the end, and
this can be one of the very powerful
ways of building distributions.
So I wanna give to you an intuition
for what exactly this means.
So in the first column,
we have two distributions.
It's either a spherical Gaussian or
a uniform distribution.
And I've chosen one particular
kind of simple function with
random parameters.
And we're gonna look at what
different kinds of these
transformations means.
And every time you do
one transformation,
you can do a number of operations
on the initial density.
You can contract the density,
as happens in the first row for
the Gaussian.
You can expand the density, which
happens after two transformations,
which allows us then
to be multimodal.
And after you do ten of
these transformations,
you have something very
complicated multimodal.
There's lots of structure,
lots of different density mass
allocated in different ways.
And the same thing for the uniform,
which actually this then,
these final distributions meet all
the requirements we want it to have.
There's complex dependencies,
there's multi-modality and
non-Gaussianity.
So some actual real functions,
here's four examples.
Let's look at the first column.
We have these two half moons.
After you do two normalizing
flows and two transformations,
Then you see we've already been
able to learn the mean and
we've already know there
are two different modes.
And we can apply as many of these
functions as we need to apply and
by K = 32,
we very well characterized and
been able to learn
the true distribution.
And I think this image gives you
a different way of thinking about
what it means to build a richer
posterior distribution.
Another way to think
about it is to say
what can I do if I
had more computation?
Can I allow my system given
more computation to learn and
to become better?
And this is sort of a theme you'll
see in many of the conferences and
talks throughout the workshop.
Especially in the deep learning
about how we can use adaptive
computation and apply it on
the fly to learn richer things and
in this case posterior distribution.
So, the key question then is.
How do you choose this function F?
We can't use any function because
we need the function to maintain.
It must be invertible and
the function needs to allow
us to learn in linear time.
So the bond is easy to adapt because
initially we can complete
the initial term,
which is just the expectation
of the factorized Gaussian.
And this log determinant term
is also easy to compute.
So we'll always start
with a simple Gaussian.
And there are a number of different
kinds of functions that we can use.
And here are three
different examples.
The first one is the one I used
in these previous example.
We call it the planar flow.
And it's just a simple function
that either allows you to learn
the identity function or a one layer
nonlinear transformation, using, for
example, a 10h layer.
You may have seen this in
other kinds of models, for
example if you are building
a large scale classifier they
would call a function like
this a residual network and
the same kind of thinking
can be used here.
There are two other kinds
of functions you can use,
one called a real non volume
preserving transformation.
And a more recent one called
an inverse autoregressive flow.
Each of these can be wide
in different ways, but
the key thing that these two
functions do is that they
ensure that the Jacobians that
you end up with are triangular.
And triangular Jacobians
have the special property
that they can always be
computed in linear time,
because all you need is handle
the diagonal of the Jacobian.
And so, these two can very powerful,
especially the last
one the inversion regressive flow
can be implemented very easily.
You can combine it with lost
of combulutional networks and
stock it and
add lots of other kinds of method.
And for any of these,
you have linear time computation
of the determinant which is what you
need to evaluate the lower bound.
And you have linear time computation
of the gradients of the free energy
of the variational object which
is what you need to do learning.
So again, just to compare, these are
the two results we had before with
the auto regressive and if we put
the result from the inverse auto
regressive to graph the flow
we can do even better.
And we can be much more flexible
depending on the amount of
computation we are willing to spend.
Again, if we look at sampling,
then we go even further.
We have even more structure,
much more diversity of color,
much more consistency
between different images.
When we look at samples in CIFAR.
So okay, there's a different
strategy you can take, and
this is a very popular one for
building modeling in general.
So when you build a model of complex
data one of the questions that you
have is what happens if I use latent
variables to make my model better.
And you will as the same question.
Can I use latent variables to make
my posterior distribution better?
And that's exactly the approach
we're going to explore here.
Which we're going to say, can I
introduce these additional variable
omega that will help me
induce some dependencies and
build a better distribution.
So, this is approach of
building hierarchical model
to represents your
posterior distribution.
I will call this hierarchical
variational models.
And unlike the previous case where
I look at all this additional
variables omega where
deterministic because they were
known transformations or
previous variables.
In this case these variables, omega,
will be stochastic variables.
But this approach now
addresses a limitation
of the normalizing flow approach.
The normalizing flow approach
can only be applied to
continuous distributions.
Because we needed this
requirement of invertible and
differentiable functions.
But with this approach we can build
much richer complex distributions.
Which can both be discrete and
continuous, or
even some mixture of the two.
And this is why this approach
now will be very appealing.
So, how we actually will think
about that is to ask the question,
if I have these additional
stochastic variables,
which have entered into my
posterior distribution.
What change would I have
made to my model so
that when I applied the rules and
principles of variational inference,
magically those variables omega
would appear in my variational bond?
So, on the left is
our original model,
the deep latent Gaussian model.
It has some latent variables Zed and
an observation model X.
This model must always
remain unchanged,
cuz this is actually the model
that through our loop of of
processing of thinking is
the one we're interested in.
So the only way we can modify that
model is to introduce a variable
omega here on the side
that's dependant on Z and X.
And if you look at this graphical
model and the distribution of omega
will be this variable which I'm
calling r, this distribution r.
So there's something
interesting here.
You can see that we call omega
now auxiliary variables, and
the graphical model tells you why.
If you observe omega,
observing omega can
never give you any information
about z, or its dependency on x.
And so, because they live outside,
they do not have a role to play
in building better models.
But the reason we are interested
in auxiliary variables,
is the impact that they have on our
inference and auxiliary variables
are one of the most powerful methods
we have for inference in general.
And once auxiliary variables do is
that, they give us very clever way
of building a mixture
model in our posterior.
They introduce correlations and
effectively what we will get is
build a distribution of mixture
of a distribution of set given x and
omega.
And by varying omega we will then
be able to vary the mixture,
which means we'll be able to
adapt to the kind of dependencies
structure that available
in our posterior.
So let's think about how we'd have
to adapt our variational method.
This is our original
variational objective.
In the top,
the first term we'll usually be
able to compute quite easily
because we just need to compute
the expectation onto some sample.
But the second term, which is
the entropy will typically be more
difficult because it
involves this term log(q).
So again we have our new
auxiliary variable model.
And since we need to build
an inference network or
think about inference we will
build two posterior distributions.
A q of omega given x and a posterior
distribution over the actual latent
variables we are interested
A Q of Zed given X and omega.
That, and this is how you can
see the mixture appearing.
And then what we will do is that,
okay, there it is, we'll
introduce a new bond which we'll
called an auxiliary variable bound.
You can see it's very simple.
From the top, we'll just make
the new joint distribution
which we'll include this
new Distribution r.
So log r.
And then we will extend the entropy
term to be the expectation over this
joint distribution.
And then what will turn out you'll
see is that this just subtracts
a non-negative term from
our original objective.
By being able to choose R and
Q in some way and
because we can learn them
through stochastic optimization,
we have the ability to make that
second character close to zero and
that is how we learn globally.
So, that's the key question for
auxiliary variable models.
We just need to choose
the auxiliary variable prior R and
the auxiliary posterior Q.
And they're lots of
different ways and
one of the ways I wanted to
point out is if you choose
r as an independent Gaussian,
it has no connections on the data.
This would call the Hamiltonian
flow, this will connect to
the previous way of thinking
about normalizing flows.
It will connect you to
ways of auxiliary variable
sampling that you already know
using Hamiltonian variational.
A Hamiltonian Monte Carlo
which you can then use
within variational inference and
can be a powerful wave,
the larger of a sampling is
also in that class of methods.
But you can obviously do better,
instead of an independent Gaussian
that has no dependency,
you can add some dependency.
You can use a Gaussian that
is dependent on some data.
You can use the auto-regressive
distribution that we combine
in the beginning.
You could use mixture models,
you could use the normalizing flow,
you could use the Gaussian process.
All of these methods
now become available.
And when you put them together,
we can build distributions that
are just as good as
anything else that we have.
With the additional flexibility
that, in this class of models,
we can handle both continuous and
discreet distribution.
And so the conclusion.
We have easy sampling,
easy evaluation of the bound and
the gradients.
We are always linear in
the number of latent variables.
And this is now one of the currently
nicest ways of doing this.
So, if we look at all
the different ways of dealing with
different posterior distributions,
we have this spectrum.
On one end, we have the true
posterior distribution that we were
trying to get to.
And we began at the very other side
with fully-factorized mean
field approximations.
And we try to take
steps to get closer and
closer to this true posterior.
We started with covariance models,
with simple structures, but
they were always Gaussians.
We use mixture models which can
typically be difficult to learn.
We used non linear order regressive
models which helped us be much
better.
And then we looked at normalizing
flows and auxiliary variable
methods which allow us to on
the fly use more computation and
build better and richer posteriors.
So, the question you will have is,
how actually will I choose my best?
We go back all the way to the
beginning of the talk to what Dave
mentioned.
This is what we call boxes loop,
this loop of thinking
about your problem,
building the simplest model starting
with the simplest kind of inference.
Understanding what is going on and
going back again, and building
more understanding, more intuition,
using richer and richer posteriors.
So, we get to the end of the talk,
and this was our summary slide.
We want to introduce you
to variational inference,
which was this approach
of learning approximate
posterior distributions in some
family of variational methods.
We introduce stochastic
optimization as the key tool
that allow us to scale variational
inference to massive datasets.
It allowed us to apply to
the widest class of problems,
especially nonconjugate and
nonlinear models,
and we're able to use very flexible
and rich posterior distribution.
Together, these things give
us a set of tools that
allow us to really scale variational
inference to modern problems.
We think this will be one of
the things that will be increasingly
important as we look to build
machine learning with higher impact
and at larger scale.
So, on behalf of myself and
Dave and Rajish, thank you for
coming this morning.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> So,
we have lots of time for questions,
maybe you guys should come up.
[LAUGH]
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Mike's there and there,
if anyone has questions.
>> You want to take
this [INAUDIBLE]?
>> Okay,
right now are there questions?
>> Is there a question?
>> Yeah, over here.
So what do you see
as the next step in
approximating the two plus theory?
What is the efforts going
forward towards that goal?
I think looking at various
approximations that don't
necessarily have analytic densities.
Like, we laid out this criteria
about meeting score functions.
Needing to be able to value
the density and sampling from them.
But there are a lot of distributions
that you can construct where you can
just simulate from them.
Working with these kinds of
approaches I think would be
pretty cool.
Yeah?
>> Hello, this question to
the last part that Shakir told.
So the two models with
auxiliary variables,
is this essentially an approach
to have an encoder and a decoder?
And in some way?
>> Yeah, so
that approach I described it in the
framework of encoders and decoders.
It can be used exactly in that
approach of amortized variational
inference and the variational
[INAUDIBLE] code framework But it's
also more general, so you haven't
seen an example yet, for example,
of applying auxiliary variables
to Bayesian neural networks,
where you want to learn
the series of parameters,
but that approach is also
applicable in that setting.
So it's, yes.
>> Thank you.
Boasion inference was,
at least when it started,
it was kind of an analytical
alternative to something.
And if I quote Devot correctly, you
used to say that boasional inference
That's what you do while waiting for
give some input to converge.
So but now in this talk,
I saw that actually some link
is being drawn into the picture.
Even in the inside inference to
convert those gradients which
are analytical and anymore Is
there any kind of convergence now
between MCMC, and
variational inference?
Would it fair to spell that
in the future a kind of
a converged model will emerge, which
nicely combines both these methods,
and it becomes just one?
>> That's a great question.
The few remarks I
would want to make, so
it's true that the old joke was that
you would derive a Gibb sampler,
start running it and while it's
converging, write pages of math
to derive your variational
inference algorithm implemented.
And if you were done
with that before the Gibb
sampler had converged, then.
You used whatever was done first.
Now you can see from this
tutorial that's really changed.
That these methods have
become much more generic,
where you write down a model and
we can, if we put either, we put it
in some conditional conjugate form.
We can immediately write down
the coordinate inference algorithm,
the for example the LDA
model I talked about.
We had a whole long
appendix deriving that.
We don't need that now.
Or working with one of these other
approximations like a score grading
or a reparameterization gradient,
without even having to do
the conditional conjugate analysis.
So it's become easier.
As you pointed out though
now sampling is in the mix.
So sampling now is part
of this variational
process though there
is a real distinction.
There are two different philosophies
to approximate inference.
Philosophies make it sound
more important than it is.
There are two different approaches
to approximate inference.
One is generating good sample.
It is creating a mark up chain
whose stationary distribution is
the target.
Here, we're using sampling as part
of the optimization procedure.
That said,
there has been some interesting
work over the last couple of years.
Maybe you guys remember
the references better than I do.
Solomons Yeah, so there's work
by Solomons and Knowles, right?
Solomons and Knowles that
tries to bring together
these two perspectives.
And there's work in the context
of stochastic variational
inference by Matt Hoffman
that uses MCMC to approximate
intractable optimal
variational distributions.
So indeed there are places where
now these two approaches to.
Approximate computation
are coming together.
>> Thank you.
>> DId you guys wanna add anything?
>> Thanks for the great tutorial.
I have a question about
the hierarchical that introduced at
the end about the direction in
this hierarchical structure And
why is about that's the Russian
matter, but it seems in
the case of causal inference it
seem the Russian doesn't matter.
And wonder, does that means we need
additional structured learning in
order to find
the hierarchical structure?
>> I think structures and
causal inference are important.
But when you build
a Hierarchal variation model.
The idea is to condition
the new things you're adding on
the structure you already believe so
that if you marginalize out that
extra stuff you still have
the structure that you actually care
about, you're just getting better
posterior approximations for
say the parameters
in your cul-de-sac.
Model.
>> In the end,
those are the variable.
The direction for
the omega is actually from
x to w which surprised me.
I thought maybe actually
omega to x as observation.
>> So I think you want that
because that's what gives you this
marginalization property
>> Where you can imagine any
graphical model you have,
the things that are at the bottom,
you can integrate out and
recover the original model, and
that's what conditioning
that way gives you.
>> You know, your question is a good
question, brings up a higher level
comment I would wanna make here,
which is that.
There are these, especially
at the end, it starts looking
like we're doing modelling in every
stage of the process, right, both
when we're building the model, and
when we're building the posterior.
And you're asking about the
structure of the posterior model,
the model of
the approximate posterior.
And you want to have different
sensibilities when you're building
these two types of models.
When you're modeling your data, then
you're really trying to simplify
your data, understand your data,
form predictions and
generalize to new data.
When you're building a model that
represents your approximating
family, you want something as
flexible as possible subject to of
course the statistical computational
tradeoff that brought up.
In one of the opening areas, I
think, in variable inference, is to
be thinking about variable inference
as this estimation problem.
What are we trading off and
how are these Two different sets
of considerations articulated, one
where we want to simplify our data
and predict the future and the other
where we want the most expressive
class of approximate posteriors that
we can still hope to do some kind
of variational optimization over.
That gives us meaningful results.
That's a good question. Hi.
Can I ask a question?
About using more complex
approximated distribution in that
main field.
I think that there are two ways
to decrease the variation of CAP.
One way is, to use a more complex
approximated distribution.
And the other is to make
the distribution that is actually
approximated, easier to approximate.
So for example, for the or
audio encoder scenario.
If we have a more complex generative
model That yields a posterior
that is more factored or say that
it is easier to approximate.
Than is there any reason to prefer
to put the complexity into a more
complex approximated distribution
rather than put in the complexity
into making this generative
model easier to approximate.
>> [INAUDIBLE] All right,
do you guys wanna make
any comments after me?
Okay.
We've agreed that I will make
a couple of comments about this.
That's a real great question.
It's kind of an age-old
question of do I want the right
answer to the wrong question or the
wrong answer to the right question?
And I think what you want is the
wrong answer to the right question.
But this is a matter of debate.
It goes back to what we
were talking about earlier,
when you're choosing a model to use,
you want to choose something that
simplifies your data and
predicts new data.
You want to not be hindered by
things like condition conjugacy,
like in [INAUDIBLE] piece and
[INAUDIBLE] piece.
But at the same time of
course as you pointed out,
that adds complexity to
the subsequent computation and
inference in optimization
that you need to make.
So there's no real good answer
to the question of when should
I make my posterior more complex or
when should I simplify my model.
I think one thing that your
question brings up is that
traditional methods of model
selection kind of go out the window.
Because we are now
evaluating our model and
our approximate inference as
a bundle and that's important.
And a lot of the results that
Chuck here showed are doing
just that, right?
We're doing some downstream
prediction because we can't
separate the choice of model from
the choice of approximate inference.
They're connected in some ways
that are hard to understand how.
And that's another
open area of course.
>> Thank you.
>> [INAUDIBLE] Was
there another one?
Okay, great.
I have a question.
Okay.
Great.
>> So variation of inference
is often criticized for
underestimating the variance.
Is there anything new that we can
actually get the right variances out
of variational inference?
Or what kind of things could we do
in order to address this issue?
>> [INAUDIBLE].
>> [LAUGH] Yeah, yeah, so
[INAUDIBLE] has some nice work
on using perturbation period to
find estimates of smooth functions.
So like a covariance is an example
using a mean field approximation.
That being said, I think these
richer approximations that Shakir
talked about can help in this way,
too.
That if you have a full
[INAUDIBLE] structure and
you transform that structure.
You have a high belief that
you'll capture the correlation
structure to the computational
cost relative to [INAUDIBLE].
>> Do you have a question?
>> So let me follow up that one
with, you guys brushed a little
quickly over how you were
evaluating your different methods.
And so I was wondering if you
could talk a little bit more about
what you're using to
evaluate right now.
What you think is the right way to
evaluate and maybe even a third
point which is criticism as
separate from evaluation.
>> I'll just start just to say
the current thing that we do.
So typically, I think this question
is the question no one can
agree on actually.
Cuz we don't actually have a good
way of evaluating our models
typically.
Because we also wanna use them for
something else and
we don't have even evaluation for
that.
So right now, all the results that I
showed always report the variational
bound instead.
Because the variational bound is at
least for that, it's good enough for
model selection and
it's consistence in that sense.
Typically, if you wanted to be very
careful, what you do is auto-compute
the true margin of likelihood by
importing sampling under the model.
And there's different ways
of doing that these days.
Maybe the easiest way to do it
is to switch to use a different
objective function.
And you can use
the difference of variational
objective which is called
the importance weighted objective or
a more generalized
variation objective.
Which will then allow you to
use the import and sampling and
then you can just send the number
of samples to very large and that
gives you a better approximation
of the true distribution.
Then of course, is the issue of what
you do with it before which is why I
show you a lot of samples.
And we do a lot of
inspection of the model but.
Probably [INAUDIBLE]
is gonna come and
say a little bit more
about the critique.
>> Yeah, I think the idea of model
criticism specific to a task
is important and there are lots
of cool ways to do it.
There's stuff like [INAUDIBLE]
predictive checking,
which asks how well do simulations
from your model match the data.
And I think in the future expanding
this to inference is also important.
Am I capturing the correlations
that are implied by my model in
my approximation?
>> Yeah,
I don't think I was gonna add much,
I mean how to evaluate this,
proceed.
We really had to evaluate
probability models is the question
you're asking about.
And that's an issue
that statisticians and
machine learners have been
discussing for 30 years.
And there's great work, for
example in the 1970s by Seymour
Geisser on predictive sample reuse
looking at log predictive
likelihoods of held out data.
That's my personal preferred
way to evaluate models
to avoid doing things like comparing
bounds and comparing approximate
inference methods, putting all
methods on the same kind of scale.
And [INAUDIBLE] mentioned
posterior predictive checks and
that we can go back to this
picture with criticized model.
Where that picture there is from a
beautiful paper by George Box called
robustness and
the statistics of science or
something like that from 1980.
And it's about how do you check your
model if you condition on data and
you get a posterior P of Z given X.
Whether or
not your model's right or wrong,
you're gonna condition on data and
get that posterior.
And so George Box said that and
this is at the highest level,
if you wanna understand whether or
not your model's doing well.
You need to step
outside of its cage and
ask yourself are those
posterior inferences good.
Now he did it in
a certain way in 1980.
Nowadays things like
held out likelihood and
other measures of generalization
error could take the place of that.
So I think that's where things
like cross validation and
held out likelihood come in.
>> There's another question.
Hello.
>> I want to relate [INAUDIBLE]
networks and [INAUDIBLE] inference.
Do you think there is some
underlying variation inference going
on in [INAUDIBLE] university and
networks when we compute that?
>> That's a good question.
>> Okay, I think there's a lot
of different ways of thinking
about this.
This is the importance
of asking a model.
So let's see,
where's a picture of a model.
So here's a picture of a model,
it is a latent variable and
then you have x.
So the key part of this model
is that you have specified
everything about it.
You have said there's some
probability of the latent variable
and you've also made
the assumption of what probability
in the world looks like.
So you've specified
the likelihood function.
And so statistically you'd
call these prescribed models.
And in this class of
prescribed models,
things like variational inference,
maximum likelihood are applicable.
Now when you go to
the adversarial network setting,
then you are in a different
class of models.
Those are models that you
call implicit models and
they don't specify this
likelihood function at the end,
they just only specify
a data generating mechanism.
And so the principle of
inference that you have to use
is different from this one.
Here, the principle of inference
is about estimating the marginal
likelihood of data and
then using that likelihood to
do other kinds of reasoning.
But when you are in implicit
models and in GANs,
the principle of
inference is different.
The principle of inference
is about comparison.
It's can you compare two samples
of data, as in two sample and
hypothesis testing, and
then give a knowledge about how
you think they are related.
Can you derive a loss function
that helps you learn?
So they are very different
principles of inference actually
going on and
thats how you [INAUDIBLE].
>> Shakira is too modest,
he posted a very beautiful paper
on the archive four days ago that
explains the intuition he
just gave here at the podium.
So to answer your question, I would
recommend looking at that paper,
Shakira's paper on the archive.
>> What paper?
>> [LAUGH]
>> Hi.
So as you mentioned in
the first part of the talk,
optimizing the variable will
lead us to a local solution.
And I'm wondering so in that respect
variational inference techniques
are known to be sensitive
to initialization.
So the question is what if I want
to be sure that I'm exploring
different optima.
So could you comment on,
is there measure of coverage
in the spatial solutions.
And I guess in that respect,
I mean having a stochastic
gradient descent might help?
Now asking these drunk people and
then well,
we are covering more space.
But how can we assure that we are
really reaching different optima?
>> So
the actual assurance is pretty hard.
So if you wanna know if
you're getting coverage,
I don't think there is
a great answer to that.
Besides running a sampler,
but even that isn't great because
the sampler will also get stuck.
In terms of getting better to and
being less sensitive to
initialization, there's a lot of
work like a kneeling, tempering.
They're both methods that
help you escape those optima.
There's new work on regularizing
the steps you take in stochastic
optimization.
So trust region methods where you
only believed that you should be
in a certain region that's feasible
given what you believe right now.
>> And I think you're right that
stochastic methods in general seem
to get the better local optima.
We saw that in many problems and
more broadly in
variational inference.
When used with non-convex
objective functions,
stochastic optimization methods
often get the better local optima
and people have theories about why.
Meambo too has some nice theories.
>> Thank you.
>> So my question is essentially.
When you're typically using
something like avation neural
network because you want to get
uncertainty estimates on your
prediction.
A lot of people do mean field
approximations on the posterior
over the weights.
That's very good when you want one
really good sample over the weights
because you are doing a mean
field with a reverse [INAUDIBLE].
But to get the [INAUDIBLE]
estimates, because
of the mean field approximation,
it might really be bad.
Are you aware of any work you see
in the posteriors over the sets
of weights?
Or more complicated posteriors
in that sense for [INAUDIBLE]?
>> Yes, I think this is one of the
most interesting questions right now
is how can you use these
new approaches for
uncertainty over distributions.
Now the difficulty is that there
are a lot of parameters that you
have to do.
These global parameters that
typically million dimensional,
10 million dimensions.
And this is why I see the failure,
that learning the [INAUDIBLE]
is not good enough,
because you just basically learn
the mean and nothing else.
So obviously, you can do things
like Monte Carlo sampling but
that doesn't really scale.
Maybe the best way right now that
people have explored is by building
ensembles of these models.
And then combining ensembles of them
because you can parallelize it very
easily and then combine the
predictive probabilities together.
But from a probabilistic and
doing a Bayesian posterior analysis,
this I think is one of the really
interesting questions.
And we'll figure them out in, I
think in the next few years [LAUGH].
>> I think we've probably
run out of time, yeah.
>> [INAUDIBLE].
>> Okay.
I think we're all set for questions.
So if you have any other questions,
you can find our speakers during
the conference but let's give
them one last round of applause.
>> [APPLAUSE]